Guide to the Peter E. Palmquist Collection of Photography and Photographic Formats
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Realia with Photographs, circa 1850-circa 1950; Series VIII; 12.6; (26 boxes)
  - Photograph Button Plaques
    - Rectangle-shaped photograph button plaque with a man in a suit and tie (Box 159, Folder 2347)
    - Circle-shaped photograph button plaque of a girl holding a cat, with a stand (Box 159, Folder 2348)
    - Oval-shaped photograph button plaque of a woman identified a Fay Jenkin Wood (Box 159, Folder 2349)
    - Circle-shaped photograph button plaque of a man with a mustache posed standing and wearing a suit and tie, with a flag in the background (Box 160, Folder 2350)
    - Circle-shaped photograph button plaque of a girl standing on a chair, framed with flowers, with a stand (Box 161, Folder 2351)
    - Sales Kits from the Cruver Manufacturing Company
      Biographical/Historical note
      The Cruver Manufacturing Company also operating under the name of the Art Medallion Co.
      - Monarch Sample Case, circa 1920 (Box 162)
      - Double Display Sample Case "A", circa 1920 (Box 163)
      - Single Display Sample Case "B", circa 1920 (Box 164)
      - Unidentified Model Sample Case, circa 1920 (Box 165)
      - Sales Sheets from the Cruver Manufacturing Company (Box 166 (Broadside))
  - Jewelry for Photographs
    This subseries includes jewelry designed to hold photographs. It consists chiefly of lockets, but includes a brooch.
    - Gold brooch missing its cover and with a swiveling photographs holder possessing two tintype portraits of two men, circa 1860-1870 (Box 167, Folder 2352)
    - Tintype of a man in an image package designed for a piece of jewelry, circa 1860-1870 (Box 167, Folder 2353)
    - Gold locket with a leaf motif on the cover, circa 1890-1910 (Box 167, Folder 2354)
    - Gold circle locket with geometrical decoration and gem stones and no photograph in it, with blindstamp "M &M," possibly made by Manton & Mole, Birmingham, England, circa 1890-circa 1910 (Box 167, Folder 2355)
    - Gold oval locket with geometrical decoration and no photographs in it, with blindstamp "L. S. 1/20 10K," possible made by Lionel Smith & Co., Birmingham, England, as well as a necklace, circa 1890-circa 1910 (Box 167, Folder 2356)
    - Gold oval locket with geometrical decoration and no photographs in it, as well as a necklace, circa 1890-circa 1910 (Box 167, Folder 2357)
    - Gold square locket with geometrical decoration and no photographs in it, circa 1890-circa 1910 (Box 167, Folder 2358)
    - Gold locket with a brown thread choker necklace and a portrait that depicts a woman, circa 1900 (Box 167, Folder 2359)
    - Gold square locket with geometrical decoration and no photographs in it, circa 1900-1920 (Box 167, Folder 2360)
    - Gold locket with geometrical decoration and two portraits that depict a man and woman, circa 1930 (Box 167, Folder 2361)
    - Gold square swiveling locket with cameo decoration on its glass cover and two portraits of the same woman, circa 1940 (Box 167, Folder 2362)
    - Gold charm with a magnifying crystal and a portrait of a male sailor, circa 1940 (Box 167, Folder 2363)
  - Cutting Tools
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    This subseries includes a razor blade and pocket knives with decorations that incorporate photographs.
    - Razor manufactured by the Novelty Cutlery Co., Canton, Ohio, with photographs of women on its scales as advertising for C. H. McIntosh, Peterboro, Ontario, circa 1890 (Box 168, Folder 2364)
    - Pocket knife probably manufactured by the Novelty Cutlery Co., Canton, Ohio, with photographs of two women on its handle cover advertising for Louis D. Gandion, San Francisco, California, circa 1910 (Box 168, Folder 2365)
    - Pocket knife manufactured in Germany with photographs of an oil derrick and the flag of the United States on its handle cover advertising for Harry John Coghlan, Taft, California, 1924 (Box 168, Folder 2366)
  - Photographs on Containers
    This subseries includes containers with decorations that incorporate photographs.
    Organized under three headings: Boxes, Trays, and Writing Equipment.
    - Boxes
      - Seashell with an accordion-folded halftone sheet of photographs depicting San Francisco, California, before and after the earthquake on April 18, 1906, circa 1907 (Box 169, Folder 2367)
      - Plastic box, probably a playing card box, with a photograph on its cover that depicts men operating a bulldozer at a logging site, probably in northern California, circa 1935 (Box 169, Folder 2368)
      - Matchbox cover with two portraits of a man identified as George Gifford of Esh Winning, England, circa 1920 (Box 169, Folder 2369)
      - Compact for cosmetics with a hand colored photograph of an automobile, circa 1930 (Box 169, Folder 2370)
    - Trays
      - Metal tray with a relief halftone portrait of two boys and advertising E. J. Blum General Merchandise in Monticello, Wisconsin, circa 1900 (Box 169, Folder 2371)
      - Metal tray souvenir from the Pan American Exposition in Buffalo, New York, created by a Bosco Photographie-Automat with a tintype portrait of a young man, 1901 (Box 169, Folder 2372)
      - Metal tray souvenir from the Louisiana Purchase Exposition in St. Louis, Missouri, but manufactured in Germany, with a relief halftone portrait of three boys and a girl, 1904 (Box 169, Folder 2373)
      - Metal tray with a relief halftone view of the Point Arena Lighthouse at Point Arena, California, circa 1910 (Box 169, Folder 2374)
    - Writing Equipment
      - Ink pen with full body portraits of two men and a mechanism that removes their clothing, circa 1975 (Box 169, Folder 2375)
      - Paper spike with a view of a church in Ylivieska, Finland, circa 1950 (Box 170, Folder 2376)
  - Ceramic Tiles and a Porcelain Plate with Photographs
    This subseries includes ceramic tiles and a porcelain plate decorated with photographs.
    - Oval ceramic tile with a portrait of a woman, circa 1900 (Box 171, Folder 2377)
    - Royal, semi-porcelain plate manufactured by Johnson Bros. England, with a portrait of a woman, circa 1900 (Box 172, Folder 2378)
    - Rectangular ceramic tile with a portrait of a woman, circa 1910 (Box 171, Folder 2379)
    - Oval ceramic tile with a a portrait of a woman and a pinlock back on the verso, circa 1910-1920 (Box 171, Folder 2380)
    - Round ceramic tile with a portrait of a small child, probably a memorial photograph for a tombstone, circa 1910-1920 (Box 171, Folder 2381)
    - Square ceramic tile manufactured by Gladding McBean & Co. with an informal portrait of a man and two women in a burro cart in Tijuana, Mexico, circa 1930 (Box 171, Folder 2382)
  - Tobacciana
    This subseries consists of photographically decorated tobacciana, which includes material related to the consumption or marketing of tobacco products, including cigarettes and matchbooks.
    - Cigarette case with an exterior portrait of a woman by a valley, circa 1890 (Box 173, Folder 2383)
    - Cigarette cards for Sweet Caporal Cigarettes manufactured by Kinney Bros., circa 1895 (Box 173, Folder 2384)
    - Advertising silks for Old Mills Cigarettes manufactured by the American Tobacco Company, circa 1910 (Box 173, Folder 2385)
    - Cigarette lighter case with views of the Blue Church in Augusta, Ontario, and the site of the Battle of the Mill in Prescott, Ontario, circa 1920 (Box 173, Folder 2386)
    - Matchbook for Eitel's Old Heidelberg Inn in Chicago, Illinois, with a portrait of a woman, circa 1950 (Box 173, Folder 2387)
    - Matchbook manufactured by the Monogram Company, San Francisco, California, with a view of a house, circa 1950 (Box 173, Folder 2388)
    - Matchbook printed with "A Merry American Christmas," and a portrait of a man, circa 1955 (Box 173, Folder 2389)
  - Paperweights
    This subseries consists of paperweights designed to hold photographs.
    - Wilfred Smith & Company, Rectangular paperweight with a view of the Chickasaw Female College, Pontotoc, Mississippi, circa 1900 (Box 174, Folder 2390)
    - Oval paperweight with a view of the Ponte Sant'Angelo in Rome, circa 1900 (Box 174, Folder 2391)
    - Circular paperweight with a studio portrait of a woman with another woman partially visible, circa 1900 (Box 174, Folder 2392)
    - Circular paperweight frame with a portrait of a woman in profile, circa 1900 (Box 174, Folder 2393)
    - Circular paperweight with no photograph, circa 1900 (Box 174, Folder 2394)
  - Photographs on Cloth
    This subseries consists of photographs on cloth, including photographically illustrated cloth incorporated into a hand fan.
    - Photograph on cloth and mounted on board, an exterior portrait of a man posed sitting and a woman posed standing in front of a blanket on the side of a house, circa 1890-circa 1900 (Box 176 (Oversize), Folder 2395)
    - Photograph on silk in a hand fan, a hand-colored portrait of a Japanese woman wearing a kimono, circa 1900 (Box 175 (Oversize))
    - Photograph on cloth, an exterior portrait of two men, five women, and a child posed with five donkeys, circa 1910 (Box 176 (Oversize), Folder 2396)
  - Photographically Illustrated Novelties
    This subseries consists of photographically illustrated novelties used as promotional material.
    - Paper hand fan with chromolithographic views of Tacoma, Washington, circa 1900 (Box 177)
    - Century of Progress International Exposition, Chicago, Illinois
      - Parisian Novelty Company, Hairbrush illustrated with views of the Century of Progress International Exposition, 1933 (Box 178, Folder 2397)
      - Premier Electric Company, "PECoptic" film viewer with 35-millimeter transparencies depicting views of the Century of Progress International Exposition, 1933 (Box 178, Folder 2398)
- Storage Containers for Photographs, 1862-1931; Series IX; 2.9; (8 boxes)
  Series IX is organized into three subseries: Photograph Mounts and Folders, Photograph Frames, and Photograph Albums.
  This series includes examples of storage containers for photographs, including folders and mounts used by photographers to market photographs, as well as frames and albums used to store and display them.
  - Photograph Mounts and Folders
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    This subseries consists of unused photograph folders, which are folded sheets of light cardboard used to cover or hold photographs made by professional photographers. Photograph mounts consist of cardboard stock used for card photographs.
    - Carte de visite mount, circa 1860-circa 1870 (Box 179, Folder 2399)
    - Gem photograph mount, circa 1870-circa 1880 (Box 179, Folder 2400)
    - Cabinet photograph mounts consisting of fifty brown mounts with gilt edges, circa 1880-circa 1890 (Box 180)
    - Card photograph mounts, circa 1900-circa 1930 (Box 179, Folder 2401-2407)
    - Photograph folders for one photographic print, circa 1900-1930 (Box 179, Folder 2408-2409)
    - Photograph folders for two photographic prints, circa 1920-circa 1930 (Box 179, Folder 2410)
  - Photograph Frames
    Organized under two headings: Metal Photograph Frames and Thread Photograph Frames.
    This subseries includes frames manufactured to hold photographs of standard sizes and typically equipped with glass (glazing) to protect the photograph and a flap attached to the back to allow the frame to stand upright on a surface.
    - Metal Photograph Frames
      - Small metal hanging frame engraved "Mountain View, Cal.," with two portraits: one portrait depicts a man and woman, the other depicts a girl, circa 1910 (Box 181, Folder 2411)
      - Small metal tabletop frame, circa 1920 (Box 181, Folder 2412)
      - Portraits in metal frames of a man and woman made by a Photomatic machine at the Union Station Building in Kansas City, Missouri, 1931 October 15 (Box 181, Folder 2413)
        2 trays
    - Thread Photograph Frames
      Photo frames created by twisting thread in geometric patterns around needles poked into cardboard
      - Thread photo frame with a studio portrait of a girl with her hands beside her face, circa 1900 (Box 181, Folder 2414)
      - Thread photo frame with a studio portrait of a girl, circa 1900 (Box 181, Folder 2415)
      - Thread photo frame with a studio portrait of a girl and a studio portrait of a boy on opposite sides of the frame, circa 1900 (Box 181, Folder 2416)
      - Two thread photo frames attached together with a studio portrait of a girl and a studio portrait of a woman, circa 1900 (Box 181, Folder 2417)
  - Photograph Albums
    Organized under two headings: Title Pages from Albums and Photograph Albums
    This subseries consists of examples of title pages from photograph albums, as well as photograph albums without extant photographic prints or photographic negatives.
    - Title Pages from Albums
      - Roberts Brothers, Boston, Massachusetts, Title pages from photograph albums, 1862-1875 (Box 182, Folder 2418)
      - Unidentified publishers, Title pages from photograph albums, circa 1860-circa 1900 (Box 182, Folder 2419)
    - Photograph Albums
      - Weck, F. A., Eureka, California, Photograph album with hand-painted edges and metal clasps, circa 1875 (Box 183)
      - Leather photograph album with a metal clasp, circa 1880-circa 1890 (Box 184)
      - Fabric trapezoidal-shaped photograph album with a metal clasp and metal ornaments on its cover, circa 1890-circa 1895 (Box 185)
      - Celluloid and fabric photograph album with a metal clasp, circa 1890-circa 1900 (Box 186)
      - Kahn, George H., San Francisco, California, Photographic film negatives album, circa 1910 (Box 187)
- Additions from Other Collections, Series X
  - Printed Material
    - Advertising for Photographic Suppliers, 31 (Box 188)
    - Articles about Photography, 9 (Box 188)
    - Panama-Pacific International Exposition, Camera licenses, 1915 (Box 188)
  - Photographic Prints by Male Photographers
    - Bennett, J. C. (Box 189)
    - Caldwell, Warren H. (Box 189)
    - Everitt's Art Gallery (Box 189)
    - [F. M.] Spencer's Art Gallery (Box 189)
    - G. L. Merrill & Co. (Box 189)
    - Hoffman, S. S. (Box 189)
    - Lewis, D. L. (Box 189)
    - Lingo, E. A. (Box 189)
    - Nilson, Axel (Box 189)
    - Ridgway, William (Box 189)
    - Sciberd & Brother (Box 189)
    - Soule, John P., 30 (Box 189)
    - W. C. A. (Box 189)
    - Weaver, O. F. (Box 189)
    - Xograf (Box 189)
    - Oversize Photographic Prints
      - J. E. Purdy & Co. (Box 192 (Oversize))
    - Photographic Prints by Subject
      - Photographic prints depicting photographers and photographic studios (Box 190)
  - Photographs by Unidentified Photographers
    - Silhouette of a woman (Box 191)
    - Tintypes, studio portraits (Box 191)
    - Cartes-de-visite, salt print (Box 191)
    - Cartes-de-visite, studio portraits of women (Box 191)
    - Cartes-de-visite, studio portraits of men (Box 191)
    - Cartes-de-visite, studio portraits of a woman and a man (Box 191)
    - Cartes-de-visite, studio portraits of groups (Box 191)
    - Cartes-de-visite, exteriors and interiors (Box 191)
    - Cartes-de-visite, copy photographs (Box 191)
    - Cartes-de-visite, religious subjects (Box 191)
    - Cabinet photographs, studio portraits of children (Box 191)
    - Cabinet photographs, studio portraits of women (Box 191)
    - Cabinet photographs, studio portraits of men (Box 191)
    - Cabinet photographs, exterior portraits (Box 191)
    - Card photographs, studio and exterior portraits (Box 191)
    - Photographic postcards, studio portraits (Box 191)
    - Photographic postcards, exteriors (Box 191)
    - Photographic prints, studio portraits (Box 191)
    - Photographic prints, interiors (Box 191)
    - Photographic prints, exteriors (Box 191)
    - Oversize photographic prints
      - Card photographs, studio portraits of children (Box 192 (Oversize))
      - Card photographs, interiors of groups (Box 192 (Oversize))
      - Card photographs, exteriors of groups (Box 192 (Oversize))
      - Photographic prints, interiors of couples (Box 192 (Oversize))
      - Photographic prints, interiors of groups (Box 192 (Oversize))
      - Photographic prints, exteriors of groups (Box 192 (Oversize))
      - Unidentified photographer, View of the Cologne Cathedral, Cologne, Germany, circa 1885 (Box 193 (Broadside oversize))
  - Photographs by Format
    - Unidentified photographer, Orotone? of a waterfall, possibly in Yosemite Valley, California (Box 194)
    - Unidentified photographer, Lantern slide in a wooden frame depicting with a hand-colored view of Mariposa Grove, California (Box 194)
    - Lantern Slides
      - A-B Slide Studios (Box 195)
      - Alta Slide Company (Box 195)
      - American Lecture (Box 195)
      - Bannett, S. H. (Box 195)
      - Binkley, E. (Box 195)
      - Bledsoe Photo Co. (Box 195)
      - Brown, B. L. (Box 195)
      - Clum, John P. (Box 195)
      - Cowlink, H. T. (Box 195)
      - Curtis, Asahel, 2 (Box 195)
      - Erwin, J. W. (Box 195)
      - Fairbanks, H. W., 2 (Box 195)
      - Gray, Edward P. (Box 195)
      - Harbach, Theo J. (Box 195)
      - Kanzee, George, 12 (Box 195)
      - Keystone View Company, 6 (Box 195)
      - Kiser, Fred (Box 195)
      - Lindeley, L. D. (Box 195)
      - Mahon, Charles, 4 (Box 195)
      - Marble, B. (Box 195)
      - Martin, Frederick W. (Box 195)
      - Maude, F. H. (Box 195)
      - Naves, Gus A. (Box 195)
      - Partridge, Sam C., 3 (Box 195)
      - Pierce, C. C. (Box 195)
      - Putnam & Valentine, 2 (Box 195)
      - Reed, George W., 2 (Box 195)
      - Rodolph, Frank B., 17 (Box 195)
      - Stone, George E., 2 (Box 196)
      - Street, W. J. (Box 196)
      - Superior Slide Studio, 14 (Box 196)
      - Waters, R. J., 7 (Box 196)
      - Weister Company (Box 196)
      - Unidentified photographers, 41 (Box 196)
      - Unidentified photographers, 66 (Box 197)
      - Unidentified photographers, 72 (Box 198)
      - Unidentified photographers, 11 (Box 199)